Guide to the Frederick Russell Burnham Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frederick Russell Burnham papers
1864-1976
MS 115
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
18.33
(30 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, writings, scrapbooks, film, and photographs documenting the personal and professional life of Frederick Russell Burnham, especially his years in Africa, and his exploration work in Mexico.
Burnham, Frederick Russell, 1861-1947
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Ilo K. Burnham, 1949. Transferred from the Hoover Institute of War, Revolution, and Peace, 1984. Gift of Mr. Frederick R. Burnham II, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and additional material: I. Correspondence, 1864-1947. II. Subject Files, 1890-1947. III. Writings, 1893-1946. IV. Personal and Family Papers, 1879-1951. V. Photographs, ca. 1893-1924.
Scope and Contents
The Frederick Russell Burnham Papers are particularly useful for the detailed information they provide on Africa, from approximately 1893 to 1911. Burnham's correspondence, and that of his wife, Blanche, his journals and diary extracts, and photographs provide written and visual observations of military life, native inhabitants and cultures, geography, and wildlife in south and western Africa. Although Burnham was an American, his views of Africa and its future, native Africans, the Boers, and the wars in which he participated, were very much in keeping with those of British imperialists, many of whom he admired, befriended, and fought alongside. There is also substantive material in his subject files, and extensive photographs, on the mining explorations and development operations he undertook in Mexico, from approximately 1905 to 1920. Blanche's life is primarily documented through the informative letters she wrote to Frederick and other relatives.
Biographical / Historical
Frederick Russell Burnham, scout, mining expert, and adventurer, was born on May 11, 1861, in Tivoli, Minnesota, to Reverend Edwin Otway and Rebecca (Russell) Burnham. After nine years of frontier life in Minnesota, during which Frederick and his mother survived an Indian attack on New Ulm, the family moved to Los Angeles. Edwin Burnham died in 1873, and Rebecca and Howard, Frederick's brother, moved back east. Frederick, however, enjoyed California so much that he chose to stay and began to acquire the outdoor skills that were to make him famous. For the next twenty years he travelled throughout the southwestern United States and Mexico. He sought out the best scouts in the regions and from them learned riding, tracking, hunting, and wilderness survival skills. His jobs ranged from mounted messenger for the Western Union Telegraph Company (when he was thirteen), to cowboy, big game hunter and seller, gold prospector, deputy sheriff, and Apache fighter.
While mining for gold in Arizona in 1893, Burnham read in the newspapers of the career of Cecil John Rhodes. Feeling he was being "summoned," Burnham, with his wife, Blanche (Blick), and son, Roderick, journeyed to the South African frontier to be of assistance to Rhodes in his endeavors. For the next four years he was a scout for Rhodes' British South Africa Company, and he fought and gained widespread fame in the two Matabele Wars. He also led exploring expeditions north of the Zambesi River and made significant discoveries of archeological ruins and fields of coal and copper. After returning to North America to mine gold in the Klondike, Burnham went back to Africa early in 1900 to serve as chief of scouts for the British army during the Boer War. Again earning fame for his exploits, and mustered out in 1900 due to injuries received in battle, Burnham was awarded the Distinguished Service Order and the South African Medal by the British government.
Burnham arrived back in the United States in 1904 and during the next three decades he lived in California and engaged in prospecting and archeological expeditions. He was particularly interested in Mexico and made several important archeological discoveries that shed light on the Maya civilization. With John Hays Hammond, the well-known mining engineer who Burnham had first met in Africa, he attempted to irrigate and cultivate the Yaqui Valley in northern Mexico, but encountered difficulties after the outbreak of the Mexican civil war in 1912. The two men were more successful in establishing the Burnham Exploration Company, which operated the productive Dominguez Hill oil field in California.
Burnham had a number of personal interests, to which he devoted a good deal of time and energy. He was a friend and admirer of Sir Robert Baden-Powell, founder of the Boy Scouts, and helped that organization spread in America. He was concerned with preserving American wilderness and was one of the original members of the California Park Commission. He also explored the importation of wild game animals from Africa to live in the American Southwest where they could provide a food alternative to beef and pork.
Burnham had little formal education, but he learned to read and write at home when he was a child. After being pursued by publishers for a number of years, Burnham wrote two books detailing his life and exploits: Scouting on Two Continents (1926) and Taking Chances (1944).
Burnham married Blanche Blick of Clinton, Iowa, in 1884, and she accompanied him on many of his trips, as did Blanche's brothers, John and Judd. He had two sons, Roderick and Bruce, and a daughter, Nada. Blanche died in 1938, and in 1943, Burnham married Ilo K. Willetts. He died on September 1, 1947, in Santa Barbara, California.
Explorers -- Africa; Africa -- Discovery and exploration; Africa; Explorers; Burnham, Frederick Russell, 1861-1947
- Correspondence, 1864-1947; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged in three sections: Family, General, and Letterbook. The Family correspondence is comprised of letters written by Frederick, generally to his wife, Blanche ("BB"); letters written by Blanche to various family members; and letters written by members of the Ingram family, into which one of Blanche's sisters married. The letters of Frederick are excellent sources of information on his trips, explorations, and military assignments, and contain fairly detailed observations of the geography he traversed, the wildlife he hunted, and the native peoples he encountered. Blanche's letters to her relatives often summarize Frederick's trips, the day-to-day routines of her family and social life, and include reports on Roderick and Bruce. Many of the letters in the series from the years 1893 to 1896 were published in An American Family on the African Frontier: The Burnham Family Letters, 1893-1896, edited by Mary and Richard Bradford.
  The General section is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Frederick remained in contact with a number of men he met and befriended in Africa, including Lord Baden-Powell, A. Kingsley Macomber, and H. Rider Haggard, and his letters to and from them often contain reminiscences of battles and military life in Africa and commentary on the future of the country. His long friendship and business collaborations with John Hays Hammond are documented in the Hammond files, and in various files in the Subjects series.
  A letterbook at the end of the series, entitled "Bulawayo, Rhodesia," holds seven letters written in 1897 by Burnham to Lord Gifford, Henry Green, and John W. Nolan. There is additional correspondence between Burnham and the three men in the General section. The letters are damaged and difficult to read, but appear to concern land and mining claims and sales in Africa.
  - Family
    - 1864-1900 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 10)
      General
      See also:Oversize Box 25
    - 1900-1908 (Box 2, Folder 11 - 20)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 3, Folder 21 - 32)
    - 1919-1945, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 33 - 39)
    - Typescripts, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - General
    - A, 1906-1946 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - B, 1895-1945 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Baden-Powell, Lady, 1900-1940 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Baden-Powell, Lord Robert, 1941-1946 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Beek, Joseph A., 1941-1945 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Bent, Arthur S., 1899-1929 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Birdwood, F. M., Lord, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Boyes, John, 1941-1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Brininstoll, E. A., 1945 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - C, 1900-1946 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Cheney, M. G., 1945 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Christie-Crawford, Arthur, 1914-1945 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Churchill, Winston, Sir, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - D, 1908-1945 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Davis, Richard Harding, 1906, undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - de Chair Family, 1929-1945 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - E, 1896-1947 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - F, 1906-1945 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Foster, T.W., 1917-1919 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Frick, Childs, 1933-1945 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - G, 1908-1945 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - George, John G., 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Gifford, Maurice, Hon.[military expedition reports], 1895 (Box 6, Folder 63 - 64)
    - Gifford family, 1896-1945 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Grant, Madison, 1911-1936 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Grey, Earl, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - H, 1900-1946 (Box 6, Folder 68 - 69)
    - Haggard, Sir H. Rider, 1891-1926 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Hammond, Harris, 1911-1936, undated (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Hammond, John Hays, 1905-1936 (Box 6, Folder 72 - 74)
      See also:Series II. Subject Files, 1890-1947 Folder 30
      See also: Series II. Subject Files, 1890-1947 Folder 31
    - Hammond family, 1910-1940 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Holder, Charles, 1909-1919 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1925-1939 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Howard, Walter, 1938-1941 (Box 7, Folder 78)
    - Hunter-Weston, Ayler, Sir, 1937-1945 (Box 7, Folder 79)
    - Hutchinson, Joseph K., 1925 (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - I, 1905, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 81)
    - Ingram, P., 1895 (Box 7, Folder 82)
    - J, 1906-1945 (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - Jamison, Leander Starr, 1895, 1906 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - K, 1912-1943 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Kinzie, R. L., 1916-1917 (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - L, 1908-1945 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Little, Stanley, 1903-1910 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Longan, Patrick, 1917-1946 (Box 7, Folder 89)
      See also: Series II. Subject Files, 1890-1947 Folder 63 - 65
    - Lord, Elliot, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - M, 1909-1946 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Mackie, W.W., 1926-1945 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Macnaughton-Jones, H., 1905-1917 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - Macomber, A. Kingsley, 1895-1945 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - Macomber, H. J., 1916-1921 (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - Mc, 1916-1945 (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Mudd, Harvey S., 1938-1942 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - N, 1905-1945 (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - O, 1909-1945 (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - P, 1909-1945 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - Perrin, E. B., 1905-1917 (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - R, 1902-1945 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Roosevelt, Archibald, 1941-1945 (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1933-1941 (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Roosevelt, Grace, 1934-1945 (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - Roosevelt, Kermit, 1930-1934 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore, Jr., 1926-1940 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - S, 1907-1945 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - T, 1908-1942 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Thompson family, 1896-1941 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Thornberry family, 1917-1943 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Troxell, L. E., 1915 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - V, 1906-1919 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - W, 1897-1945 (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Whitcomb, R. E., 1908 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Y, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - Unidentified, 1900-1919, undated (Box 8, Folder 117)
  - Letterbook, "Bulawayo, Rhodesia", 1897 (Box 8, Folder 118)
- Subject Files, 1890-1947; Series II
  The series is arranged alphabetically by corporate names, individuals' names, topics and primarily documents Burnham's mining, oil, and exploration pursuits in Africa and Mexico, especially after the Boer War. The various company, syndicate, land, and mining folders mostly contain correspondence, contracts, and financial transaction records. Occasionally, however, there are reports, written by Burnham or field agents, which provide detailed descriptions of various geographical areas. The Yaqui Project folders document the efforts by Burnham and Hays Hammond to cultivate the Yaqui Valley in Mexico and the difficulties they encountered with the local Indians during the Mexican civil war. The series also documents Burnham's personal interests in such matters as animal importation, the Boy Scouts, and his efforts during World War I to recruit men for a military division headed by former President Theodore Roosevelt (the government rejected Roosevelt's offer to lead a division to France).
  - Animal conservation and importation, 1905-1911 (Box 9, Folder 1 - 3)
    General note
  - Banda Syndicate, 1901-1904 (Box 9, Folder 4 - 5)
  - Bardeen Oil Company, 1919-1924 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Belingive Development Syndicate, 1911 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Boy Scouts of America, 1931-1947 (Box 9, Folder 8 - 11)
  - British South Africa Company, 1890-1911 (Box 9, Folder 12 - 13)
  - Burnham Exploration Company, 1924-1933 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Carmichael, John Gordon [primarily correspondence between Carmichael and H. Rider Haggard, and Carmichael manuscripts], 1894-1897, n.d (Box 10, Folder 15 - 18)
  - Chilean gold mines, 1916-1918 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Chinese expeditions, 1898-1907 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - East Africa Syndicate
    - Correspondence, 1902-1920 (Box 10, Folder 21 - 23)
    - Contracts, 1902-1912 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Reports, 1904-1920, undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Miscellaneous, 1898-1903, undated (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Elephant hunting, 1903 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Guggenheim Exploration Company, 1905-1906 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Hammond, John Hays
    - Clippings, 1913-1936 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence [re: Secretary of Commerce campaign], 1921 (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence [re: Secretary of Interior campaign], 1923 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - International Petroleum Company, 1911-1919 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - La Caridad Mines, 1906 (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - Louisiana oil interests
    - General, 1920-1921 (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Letterbook, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Macomber museum collection, 1940-1944 (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Manganese Company of California, 1916-1917 (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Manganese properties, 1917 (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Map [Bloemfontein, South Africa; hand-drawn map and handwritten battle report on verso], 1900
    See: Oversize Box 25
  - Mexican Seaboard Oil Company, 1922-1924 (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - Mexican Southern Mining Syndicate, 1905-1908 (Box 11, Folder 40 - 42)
  - Mining
    - Consultants, 1909-1921, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 43)
    - Maps, 1900, undated (Box 11, Folder 44)
      See also: Oversize Box 26
    - Reports
      - Mexico, 1904-1906 (Box 11, Folder 45)
      - United States, 1907-1921 (Box 11, Folder 46)
  - Moulton Irrigated Lands Company, 1917 (Box 11, Folder 47)
  - National Rifle Association, 1942-1943 (Box 11, Folder 48)
  - Pao Verde Valley lands, 1916-1920 (Box 11, Folder 49)
  - Redfield Mines, 1911-1916 (Box 12, Folder 50)
  - Rhodes, Cecil [writings about Rhodes, probably by Burnham], undated (Box 12, Folder 51)
  - Richardson Construction Company, 1921-1922 (Box 12, Folder 52)
  - Riverbend Ranch [Burnham's ranch on the San Joaquin River]
    - Contracts, 1911-1920 (Box 12, Folder 53 - 54)
    - Correspondence, 1915-1921 (Box 12, Folder 55 - 57)
  - Riverside County Real Estate
    - Correspondence, 1916-1920 (Box 12, Folder 58)
    - Financial, 1913-1921 (Box 12, Folder 59)
  - Rocky Mountain Club, undated (Box 12, Folder 60)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore [re: attempts to raise an Army division to fight in World War I]
    - Applications, undated (Box 12, Folder 61)
    - Clippings, 1914, 1917, 1919, undated (Box 12, Folder 62)
    - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 63 - 65)
  - Scouting [writings by Burnham], undated (Box 13, Folder 66)
  - Sonora lands, Mexico, 1906-1909 (Box 13, Folder 67)
  - Southwest Museum, 1944-1945 (Box 13, Folder 68)
  - Tungsten mining, 1916 (Box 13, Folder 69)
  - Wa Syndicate, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 70 - 71)
  - Western Mexico Development Syndicate, 1906-1910, undated (Box 13, Folder 72)
  - Wheeler Land Company, 1909-1921 (Box 13, Folder 73)
  - Yaqui Land and Water Company, 1906-1917 (Box 13, Folder 74 - 75)
  - Yaqui project, 1908-1941 (Box 13, Folder 76 - 79)
- Writings, 1893-1946; Series III
  This series is comprised of Frederick Burham's various writings, published and unpublished.The Deletions folder under Taking Chances, and the Articles contain writingsabout American Indians, scouting, hunting, and several interesting individuals he met on his explorations.
  - Scouting on Two Continents
    - Typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 1 - 4)
    - Dust covers, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Taking Chances
    - Typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 6 - 8)
    - Deletions, 1943, undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Articles, 1896-1946, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Journals
    - Northern vs. southern exploration, undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - "Trek to Victoria", 1893 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Africa [includes clippings], 1893 (Box 16)
  - Speeches, 1922-1939, undated (Box 17, Folder 13-16)
- Family and Personal Papers, 1879-1951; Series IV
  The series is arranged alphabetically, by name of family member. The most informative materials are the diaries of John Blick and Frederick (which should be used in conjunction with his journals in the Writings series), which detail African expeditions. The diary of Rebecca Burnham (Frederick's mother) mostly describes her social life in California and England during the years 1895 and 1896.
  - Blick, John Charles
    - General, 1921-1922, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Diary [West Africa mining expedition], 1901 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Burnham, Blanche Blick [diary, few entries; passport; teaching certificates], 1879-1938, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
    See also: Oversize Box 25
  - Burnham, Frederick Russell
    - Address book, 1929 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Biographical [articles about Burnham, including obituaries], 1895-1951, undated (Box 18, Folder 5 - 6)
    - Condolences [cards and letters written upon his death]
      - General, 1947-1948, undated (Box 18, Folder 7 - 9)
      - General, 1947-1948, undated (Box 19, Folder 10 - 11)
      - Boy Scouts of America, 1947 (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - Burnham family, 1947 (Box 19, Folder 13)
      - Southwest Museum, 1947-1948 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Diary [typescripts], 1893, 1895, n.d (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Financial, 1895-1921 (Box 19, Folder 16 - 17)
    - Legal, 1895-1939, undated (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - Memorabilia
      - General, 1898-1935, undated (Box 20, Folder 19)
      - African[?] [artifacts: scale and weights; bracelets; plaque; geological fragments; small carvings], undated (Box 21)
      - Boy Scouts of America [Award of the Silver Buffalo], 1936 (Box 22, Folder 20)
      - Freemasonry [includes certificate], 1898 (Box 22, Folder 21)
    - Military, 1900-1904 (Box 22, Folder 22)
    - Notebooks, 1920, undated (Box 22, Folder 23)
    - Passport, 1935 (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - Burnham, Mather Howard [re: estate], 1920-1922, undated (Box 22, Folder 25)
  - Burnham, Rebecca [diaries kept in California and England], 1895-1896 (Box 22, Folder 26)
  - Ingram, Pearl [claims agreements], 1895 (Box 22, Folder 27)
  - Unidentified
    - Notebooks, undated (Box 22, Folder 28)
    - Notes, undated (Box 22, Folder 29)
    - Trip book [probably by Burnham], 1935 (Box 22, Folder 30)
- Photographs, Circa 1893-1924; Series V
  The series is arranged in two sections: people and places. Both sections contain quite good photographs of the geography, animal life, and native inhabitants of Africa and Mexico, although some of the photographs in the Yaqui folders are fading.
  - People
    - Blick, John [trip in Mexico, includes landscape photographs], 1908 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Burnham, Frederick Russell [portrait], undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Wilson's Patrol, Circa 1893
  - Places
    - "African Life" [album, includes photographs of Kaffir men and women, Massai warriors, Boer War military encampments, and wildlife], undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Australia, 1924 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - East Africa, 1902-1903 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - West Africa, 1901 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Yaqui, Mexico, 1907, undated (Box 24, Folder 7 - 17)
- Oversize
  - Oversize materials (Box 25)
  - Maps (Folder 26)
- Additional Material, 1894-1941; Accession 2012-M-057
  - Scrapbook, 1894-1930 (Box 1)
  - Yosemite National Park, Undated; 1 (Box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Cabeza Prieta Wildlife Park scrapbook, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Photographs and drawings, 1894-1930 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notaria del Lic. Ignacio Razon, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - News clippings, 1908-1927 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Focus on Rhodesia, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Roderick Burnham drawings, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)